Guide to the Gambia Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gambia collection
1889-2007
MS 1518
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.52
(7 boxes)
The collection consists of a ship's logbook and printed material relating to the history of Gambia and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a ship's logbook and printed material relating to the history of Gambia and the current political, economic, and social conditions.
Women -- Gambia; Gambia -- Description and travel; Gambia -- Economic conditions; Gambia -- Politics and government; People's Democratic Organisation for Independence and Socialism; Peoples' Progressive Party (Gambia)
- Inventory, 1889-1892, 1961-1993
  - Private log of H.M.S. Archer kept by J. S. Berry, 1889-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Government documents; journals; reports, 1961-1970, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Political organizations: journals; newsletters; printed material, [1978]-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: printed material, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women's movement/organizations: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The People's Democratic Organization for Independence and Socialism (P.D.O.I.S.): journals; newsletters; printed material, 1986-1988, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Periodicals, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Social welfare organizations: journals; newsletters; printed material, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional Material, 1940-1995, undated; Accession 1995-M-145
  - Additional printed materials, 1940, 1958, 1965, 1984, 1994-1995, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1976-1998, undated; Accession 2004-M-039
  - Female Circumcision [booklet], Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Gambia Magazine [special eleventh independence anniversary issue], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Gambia Outlook [newsletter], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Gambia Times [Peoples Progressive Party], 1984 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "History of Fort Bullen"/"History of James Island" [pamphlets], Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Le Messager Africain [special Gambia issue], Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Nation [newsletter], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - People's Democratic Organization for Independence and Socialism (P. D. O. I. S.\) [mission statement, party structure, etc.], 1986, 1992, 1996, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Waxtaani Xalel Yi" [National Library of the Gambia], 1979, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, 1980-1994; Accession 2006-M-038
  - Awa: The Gambia Women's Development Journal, vol. 5 [ceased in 1994], 1994 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Gambian, vol. 4 and supplementary edition, 1988 Nov, December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Islamic Cultural Club, Gambia High School, Al' Nidar 'The Call' Magazine [student essays], [1993] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Quinn, Bowden, "A Last Look at The Gambia," Institute of Current World Affairs, 1980 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Toiler: Voice of the Worker, vol. 2, The Gambia Workers' Confederation, 1988 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1964; Accession 2010-M-106
  - Supplement to The Gambia News Bulletin, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2015-M-001; 2.02
  - Printed material, 1988-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)